does lack of sleep cause you to gain
weight is there a connection between
sleep and weight gain or weight loss
these next two videos will help answer
that question
[Music]
population Studies have found short
sleep duration has been associated with
obesity in both children and adults
observational studies can never prove
cause and effect though maybe the
Obesity is leading to sleep loss instead
of the other way around
obesity can cause arthritis acid reflux
and apnea all of which can interfere
with sleep the relationship between
obesity and sleep apnea where you're
breathing repeatedly stops and starts
throughout the night may be explained by
increased tongue fat fat deposited
inside the base of the tongue that may
contribute to obstructing your Airway
when you sleep on your back
the reverse causation explanation of the
link between obesity and inadequate
sleep is bolstered by the finding that
weight loss interventions can improve
daytime sleepiness
potential confounding factors also
abound for example people with lower
socioeconomic status often work less
desirable hours such as rotating or
overnight shifts or may live in noisier
neighborhoods with poorer air quality
more crime the link between inadequate
sleep and obesity persists after
controlling for these kinds of factors
but you can't control for everything you
can't know for sure if sleep deprivation
leads to weight gain until you put it to
the test have people pull an all-nighter
and they get hungrier and choose larger
portions randomize people to shave even
just a few hours of sleep off every
night they start eating an average of
677 calories more a day compared to the
normal sleep control group other
individual responses vary widely
anywhere from eating 813 calories less
per day to as many as 1437 calories more
on average studies found sleep
deprivation LED people to overeat by
about 180 to 560 calories a day
where strict people sleep and they also
start craving unhealthier choices more
snacks more foods that are fatty and
sugary stick people in a brain scanner
after staying awake all night or after a
few nights of four hour sleep and the
reward Pathways light up brighter in
response to high calorie foods sleep
deprivation bumps the levels of the
chief endocannabinoid in the body the
natural chemical we synthesize that
binds to the same receptors as the
active ingredient in marijuana this may
help explain the nighttime nibbling
on the calories outside of the equation
some short sleepers may take the extra
time to exercise others will be so
sleepy they exercise less the extra
wakefulness May raise calorie
expenditure up to about 100 calories a
day but if sleep deprived individuals
are overeating hundreds of calories over
time sleep deprivation may end up
putting the wide in wide awake
with insufficient sleep inadvertently
leading to such higher calorie intake
it's no surprise that four out of five
studies involving as few as two to five
nights of sleep restriction found an
increase in body weight in other words
if you sleep less you may gain more
okay but here is where it gets crazy
even if you control calorie intake you
still lose more fat when you get more
sleep overweight subjects who normally
got between six and a half to eight and
a half hours of sleep a night were
randomized to two weeks of either eight
and a half hours to sleep at night or
five and a half hours of sleep on the
same calorie controlled diet then the
group switched and spent another two
weeks in the opposite regimen so they
spent a month living in the labs so
their diets and sleep could be totally
controlled and monitored and just
looking at the scales sleep duration
didn't seem to matter during both
periods they ate the same number of
calories and lost the same amount of
weight but most of the weight lost while
getting eight and a half hours was fat
whereas most of the weight loss when
only getting five and a half hours of
sleep at night was lean body mass same
diet but with more sleep they ended up
losing more than twice as much body fat
so you snooze you lose fat
[Music]
thank you